是, 大臣  第1季第4集
【字幕翻译 校对 调轴】:
七月 | i1984 | ox
专制国家 (老大哥是奥威尔所著1984
中的独裁者象征 已成为专制的代名词)
摄制准备 一分钟后开始录制
Recording in one minute. Studio stand by.
我们会讨论削减政府的铺张浪费 对吗
We'll talk about cuts in government extravagance, aren'twe?
在结束国家资料库的相关问题后
We'll get to that if we've got time
如果还有时间我们就展开这个话题
afterthe National Data Base.
我可不觉得民众对资料库会感兴趣
I don't think people are really interested in the Data Base.
太琐碎了
It's so trivial.
摄像机就位
VTrunning.
这是干吗?      你的脸看上去太红了(pink有左倾之义)
What's the matter? You look a bit too pink.
脸红可不行 《每日电讯报》会怎么评论?
We can't have that, whatwould the Daily Telegraph say?
铺天盖地的"我们正在迈向极权国家?"
All those questions about "are we creating a police state?"
相信我 这点可以忽略      吉姆 你了解我
We can do without those. Jim, you knowme.
我不会事先透露提问内容
I don't give out my questions in advance.
请都保持安静
Dead silence, please.
10秒倒数
Ten seconds...
5 4 3 2 …
Five. Four. Three. Two...
晚上好
Good evening.
老大哥正在监视你吗? 更准确来说
Is Big Brotherwatching you? To be more precise,
你知不知道政府正在建立你的档案库
the Government is building up a dossieron you.
还起了个听上去并无危害的名字
It's called by the harmless name of
"国家综合资料库"
"National Integrated Data Base".
只需轻轻一按 任何公务员都能
At the press of a button any civil servant
查阅你一生中的每个微小环节
can inspect just about every detail of your life
纳税 病史档案 失业次数
yourtax, yourmedical record, periods of unemployment,
孩子的成绩 一应俱全
children's school records, and that civil servant
而这个公务员可能恰好是你的邻居
may happen to be yourneighbour.
人们日益关注这一由计算机革命
There's been mounting concern overthis powerful,
为政府带来的强有力的
even totalitarian weapon that the computer revolution
极权主义武器
has put into the Government's hand.
而挥舞这根大棒的人就是
And the man who wields the weapon is the Minister
行政事务大臣 下院议员詹姆斯・哈克阁下
forAdministrative Affairs, the Right Honourable James Hacker.
大臣 我们正为一个极权国家添砖加瓦吗
Now, Minister, are we laying the foundations of a police state?
我很高兴你问了这个问题
You know, I'm glad you asked me that question.
那么 大臣 我们能得到答复吗
Well, Minister, could we have the answer?
当然可以 我正要回答 如果可以的话
Well, yes of course, I'm about to give it to you, if I may.
正如我所说 我很高兴你询问了这个问题
As I said, I'm glad you asked me that question.
因为
Because...
这个问题
it's a question
许多人在问
a lot of people are asking.
为什么呢?
And why?
因为大家愿闻其详
Because a lot of people want to know the answerto it.
就不转弯抹角了
And let's be quite clearabout this without beating about the bush,
这个问题明摆着的事实就是
the plain fact of the matter is
它的确极其重要
that it's a very important question indeed
民众有权知道
and people have a right to know.
可是大臣 我们还是没能闻其详
But Minister, we haven't yet had the answer.
不好意思 问题是什么?
I'm sorry, whatwas the question?
好吧 假设我在访谈中激怒了你
Now look, supposing I annoy you in this interview,
我怎么知道你不会回到办公室
how do I know you won't go back to youroffice,
轻轻一按 提出我的纳税记录
press a button and call up my tax records,
医疗记录 违归记录
my hospital records, my police record...
不会 不会
Oh no. No. No.
鲍勃 这不是我们国家的做事方式
Bob, that's not the way we do things in this country.
如果资料库不是用来核查民众 那是做什么用的呢?
What's the Data Base for if it's not to check up on people?
你看 这是个非常有趣的问题
You know, that's a very interesting question.
是用来保存信息
It's forstoring information
加速政府的运转
so as to speed up government business
我们就无需雇佣庞大数量的文案人员
so thatwe need not take on an enormous influx of clerical staff.
计算机是个大进步 是佳音
Computers are big business and are good news.
可是 大臣 你要是把信息输入机器
But, Minister, if you put information into the machine,
你有朝一日就会从机器中读出这些信息
you'll eventually take information out of the machine.
这倒未必
Not necessarily.
这么说 你花了2千5百万英镑
So, you're going to spend 25 million pounds
收集信息却永远不用?
accumulating information and neveruse it?
不是 是的 不是
No. Yes. No.
会有安全措施的
Well, there will be safeguards.
例如?
Such as?
镜头拉近  他在躲闪鲍勃的问题
Close in on him, Two. Bob's got him on the run.
摄制 1分45
One minute 45, studio.
我们会关注所有的可能性
We'll be looking at a whole range of possibilities.
当然 这是件复杂并具有高科技的事情
And of course, it's a complex and highly technical matter.
冰冻三尺非一日之寒啊
Rome wasn't built in a day.
还在审核中
It's underreview.
当然 这需要假以时日
And of course, these things take time.
大臣 我是在与《改革》的前任编辑谈话
Minister, am I talking to the formereditorof Reform
还是在和一个公务员发言人呢?
orto a Civil Service spokesman?
我们还没就我提到的安全措施展开论述
We haven't talked about the safeguards I've introduced.
例如 我新成立的行政监察办
And there's my newbureaucratic watchdog office, for instance.
看似不久我们会需要一大群看门狗了
It doeslook asif we'll needa whole pack of watchdogs before long.
还是十分感谢
But thank you very much.
好啦 请稍等片刻 我们要核对录影
Right, hold it there while we check the tape.
如何? 我想第一节进展的非常好
How did it go? Well, I thought... First class Very good indeed.
我似乎扯多了
I thought I waffled a bit.
不 大臣 你"太极"打得好极了
Oh no, you stonewalled superbly, Minister.
去喝一杯?
Time fora drink?
安全措施展开论述
About the safeguards I've introduced.
例如 我新成立的行政监察办
My newbureaucratic watchdog office, for instance.
看似不久我们会需要一大群看门狗了
It sounds as if we'll need a pack of watchdogs before very long.
还是十分感谢
But thank you very much.
下周的话题...
In next week's topic...
我表现如何?     大臣 棒极了
Howwas I?         Splendid, Minister.
非常庄重 非常得体
Very dignified. Very suitable.
是的 汉弗莱爵士 祝贺你
Yes, Sir Humphrey, I congratulate you.
吉姆现在训练有素
Jim is nowperfectly house trained.
你告诉他什么他就说什么
He does exactly what you tell him.
打断一下 威瑟尔先生      埃瑟尔
Lf you'll excuse me, Mr. Weasel. Weisel.
你简直就成了公务员的传声筒了
You say everything the Civil Service programmes you to say.
你是人还是喉舌?
What are you a man ora mouth?
很好笑 弗兰克
Very amusing, Frank.
一个政治顾问理解这或许不易
It might be hard fora Political Advisorto understand this,
但我只是个公务员
but I am merely a Civil Servant,
无非是遵照主子的指示
I simply do as I am instructed by my master.
如果部长是个女人你怎么称呼她?
If the Minister's a woman what do you call her?
这的确有趣
Yes, that's rather interesting.
我们想过解决的方法
We sought an answer
1947年我担任首席私人秘书时
when I was Principal Private Secretary and
伊迪丝・萨默基尔博士
Dr. Edith Summerskill,
她于1947年被委任为大臣
as she then was, was appointed Minister in 1947.
我不太愿意称她为我的"主母"
I didn't quite like to refer to heras my Mistress.
怎么解决的?      还没有定论
Whatwas the answer? We're still waiting for it.
还在审核 对吗? "冰冻三尺非一日之寒"
It's underreview, is it? Rome wasn't built in a day.
"这需要假以时日"     我得走了 大臣
These things take time. I must be going.
我也是      您走之前 我想提醒您
Me too. Before you go Minister may I remind you
别忘了明早8点在帕丁顿饭店见
we meet tomorrowmorning at Paddington at 8?
去哪?     斯旺西(威尔士南部港市) 大臣
Where are we going?      Swansea, Minister.
您将在市财政会议上发表演说
You're addressing the Conference of Municipal Treasurers.
对
Oh, yes.
可是吉姆 你要去纽卡斯尔补缺选举致词
You're due in Newcastle to address the by election meeting.
的确如此     可您无法两个都去
So I am.       You can't do both.
我不能两个都去     吉姆 那不过是公务员的野餐
I can't do both. That's a Civil Service junket.
补缺选举才重要      补缺选举很重要
The by election's important. It's important.
大臣 会议记录在您的行程表中几周了 他们很期待您的到访
The Conference is in yourdiary. They expect you in Swansea.
纽卡斯尔期待您的到访
They expects you in Newcastle.
伯纳 他怎么会有两个约会?     伯纳 我怎么会有两个约会?
How come he's double booked? How come I'm double booked?
主要是纽卡斯尔的事没人告诉我
Well, largely because nobody told me about Newcastle.
你为什么不告诉他?     你为什么不?
Why didn't you tell him? Why didn't you?
我可记不住每件事
I can't remembereverything.
弗兰克 我最好去斯旺西
Frank, I think I'd bettergo to Swansea.
决定了?      是的 最终决定
Is that a decision? Yes, that's final.
首相希望您去纽卡斯尔
The P. M. Expects you to go to Newcastle.
首相?
The P. M?
伯纳 我最好去纽卡斯尔
I think I'd bettergo to Newcastle, Bernard.
决定了 吉姆?     是的 最终决定
Is that a decision, Jim? Yes, that's final.
那我回家了     这是最终决定吗?
Now I'm going home. Is that a decision?
不不 说真的
No, quite seriously...
我想您做了错误的决定 大臣
I think you've made the wrong decision.
您到访斯旺西已经对外宣告
Yourvisit to Swansea's been announced.
您不能取消     天哪
You can't get out of it. Oh, Lord!
找到一个让我从斯旺西到纽卡斯尔的途径
Find a way of getting me from Swansea to Newcastle.
汽车 火车 直升机 随便什么 我两个都去
Car, train, helicopter, anything. I'll have to do both.
现在我回家 这是最终决定
And now I'm going home, and that is final!
最后的最后决定?     不再更改
Finallyfinal?                Absolutelyfinally.
大臣 希望您今晚能把这些盒子批完
If you could do all yourboxes tonight.
全是兼并重组委员会的文件 信件本周要回      好
There's all the M&A Committee papers and all the letters.
如果你做个乖孩子 糖果奖励
And if you're a good boy, you'll get a sweetie.
好
Good.
你好 亲爱的
Hello, darling.
谢谢 乔治 晚安       晚安 先生
Thanks, George. Goodnight. Goodnight, sir.
你好 亲爱的       你好
Hello, darling.           Hello.
终于要离我而去了?
Leaving me at last?
你忘了明天是我们结婚的周年纪念?
It's ouranniversary tomorrow, have you forgotten?
不会 当然没有忘
No, of course I haven't forgotten.
我们要去巴黎 哦 老天
We're going to Paris. Oh, my God!
你忘了      不 我没有
You had forgotten. No, I hadn't.
没有 只是我...  我不能 我有两个...
No, it's just that I... I didn't... I'm double...
我明天要去斯旺西      斯旺西?
I'm going to Swansea tomorrow. Swansea?
还有纽卡斯尔
And Newcastle.
我不想在周年纪念去那儿
I don'twant to go there formy anniversary.
不 没有你 我独自去
No. Not you. Just me.
推掉      不行
Cancel them! I can't.
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
取消 我们三个月前就决定了
Cancel them! We booked this three months ago.
不行      那我就自己去巴黎
I can't. Then I'll go to Paris without you.
你好 伯纳 对 是我
Hello, Bernard... Yes, it's me...
听着 明天的行程不得不取消
I'm going to have to cancel tomorrow.
斯旺西和纽卡斯尔
Swansea and Newcastle.
明天是我妻子的结婚周年纪念
It's my wife's wedding anniversary tomorrow...
也是你的
It's yours too!
对 实际上也是我的 对 就是这样
Yeah, and mine too actually. Yes, it is.
什么真巧? 别傻了
Coincidence? Don't be silly.
总之 明天我去巴黎 最终决定
Anyway, I'm going to Paris tomorrow and that's final.
是的 我是说过 但这次是最终的
Yes, I said that before, but this time is final!
你要使出全身解数摆平
You'll just have to cope as best as you can.
没错
Yes?
对 很明确
Yes... definitely...
对
Yes...
明白了?
Is that clear?
好的
Right!
我们去巴黎
We're going to Paris.
不 我要去斯旺西和纽卡斯尔
No, I'm going to Swansea and Newcastle.
今晚在电视上看到我了?     我倒是看到有个人像你
See me on TV tonight? I saw somebody who looked like you.
这话的意思是?      什么也不是
What's that meant to mean?     Nothing.
弗兰克说我成了公务员的传声筒
Frank says I've become a Civil Service mouthpiece.
是啊      "是啊"是什么意思?
Yes.          What do you mean, yes?
就是是啊      你是说你同意?
Well... yes.           You mean you agree?
当然      "当然"是什么意思?
Of course.       What do you mean, of course?
你还不如雇人去讲话 没准比你讲的好呢
You could have hired and actor to say it all foryou.
你何不用橡皮图章来签信件
And why not just sign your letters with a rubberstamp?
或者让你的助理代劳
Orget an Assistant Principal to sign them foryou.
反正就是他们写的
They write them anyway.
我的信才不是助理写的呢
Assistant Principals do notwrite my letters!
是副秘书写的
UnderSecretaries do that.
我放弃申辩了 大人
I rest my case, my lord.
你认为我成了傀儡?      是的 我认为是
You think I've become a puppet?      Yes, I do.
也许该让芝麻街的猪小姐做你的工作 她至少比你漂亮
Get Miss Piggy to do yourjob. She's prettier.
我不知如何是好
I don't knowwhat to do.
我被工作困住了
I'm just swamped by the work.
安妮 我真郁闷
Oh, Annie, I'm so depressed.
既然我们不去巴黎
As we're not going to Paris,
至少今晚去街角的饭店吃顿安静的晚餐
let's at least go out fora quiet little dinnertonight.
我不能
No, I can't.
伯纳要我今晚搞定三个红盒子
Bernard's told me to get through three boxes.
什么叫伯纳要求你?
What do you mean, Bernard's told you?
在《改革》做编辑的时候 你可不是这样的
When you edited "Reform" you were quite different.
你走进去 吩咐底下人怎么做
You went in, you told people what to do,
说你要什么 他们就准备什么
and you got what you wanted!
你不先发制人就会被骑在头上
Eitheryou get them by the throat orthey get you by the throat!
那段日子你撕毁多少文章?
Howmany articles did you tearup in those days?
几十篇      那你现在撕毁过多少公文?
Dozens. And howmany official papers?
这是不允许的      不允许?
I'm not allowed to! Not allowed to?
亲爱的 你是大臣 可以为所欲为
Darling, you're the Minister, you can do anything you like.
不 汉弗莱 弗兰克是对的
No, Humphrey, I've decided that Frank was right.
鲍勃・麦肯齐也是
And Bob McKenzie too.
国家数据库必须用其他的方式建立
The National Data Base has got to be organised differently.
是的 大臣
Yes, Minister.
确保安全措施到位
We want all possible built in safeguards.
是的 大臣      立刻
Yes, Minister.      Right away.
"立刻"的确切意思是?
What precisely do you mean, right away?
就是马上执行
I mean right away.
懂了 你是指马上执行 大臣?
I see, you mean right away?
汉弗莱 确保到位     好的 大臣
Got it in one, Humphrey. Well, Minister...
或许我该提醒您 我们还尚在内阁成立初期
We are still in the early months of this Government.
还有许多工作...
And there's an awful lot to get...
汉弗莱 资料库的规章必须现在更改
The Data Base rules have got to be changed. Now!
可是您不能 大臣     不 我能 我是大臣
But you can't, Minister. Yes, I can, I'm the Minister.
是的 大臣 您确实是
Yes, indeed you are, Minister.
而且是一位卓越的大臣
And quite an excellent Ministerat that.
汉弗莱 别奉承了
Nevermind the soft soap, Humphrey.
我要让所有公民都有权利查阅自己的档案
I want all citizens to have a right to see theirown files
我要立法惩治未经许可的违规查阅
and I want legislation to make unauthorised access, illegal.
好的 大臣 就这么办     好极了
Very well. It shall be done. Good.
但要立法授权公众采取法律行动
But the legislation necessary to give the public the right
要通过十分繁杂的手续
to take legal action is extremely complicated
还要耗费大量时间来起草
and would take considerable time to draft,
宣传 颁布
promulgate and enact.
公民查阅自己的档案无需立法 对吗
Legislation isn't necessaryfora citizen to see his own files, is it?
是的     那就从这开始
No... Then, we'll startwith that.
好吧 我们会争取快点实施 大臣
I suppose we could manage that slightly quicker,
但还存在许多管理上的难题
but there's an awful lot of administrative problems as well.
汉弗莱 先前对此肯定有过研究
This must have been examined before.
多年前资料库就在筹备中
The Data Base has been in preparation foryears.
肯定就此展开过讨论
There must have been discussions about it.
确实有 大臣      达成的结论是?
Yes, indeed. What conclusions were reached?
汉弗莱 达成的结论是?
Humphrey, what conclusions were reached?
我的前任对此抱何态度?
What did my predecessor want to do about it?
汉弗莱 你能听到我说的吗?
Humphrey, can you hearme?
我必须守口如瓶
My lips are sealed.
再说一遍?
I beg yourpardon?
我不能公开先前的计划 大臣
I am not at liberty to reveal previous plans, Minister.
为什么不能?
Why not?
大臣 您愿意把您在办公室的一言一行
Would you like everything that you have said in this office
都告知随后接任您职务的对手吗?
to be revealed subsequently to one of youropponents?
明白 不
I see. No.
我们不能给您对手政治弹药来对付您 反之亦然
We cannot give youropponents political ammunition against you.
可我的前任汤姆・萨金特
But Tom Sargent was my predecessor.
与我是一个党派的 他不会介意的?
It isn't a party political mattersurely?
原则问题 大臣 不能公开
It's a matterof principle. It justwouldn't be...
我明白 我们不能开这种...
I see and we don'twant to do anything thatwouldn't be...
不行
No.
打扰下 大臣     什么事 伯纳?
Oh, excuse me, Minister.      Yes, Bernard?
小问题 大臣
A slight problem, Minister.
由于反对的声浪
Because of the adverse...
就是说 您的访谈并没有获得一致的赞同
not entirelyfavourable press reaction to your interview,
其他频道想让您上他们的节目
the otherChannel wants you fortheirprogramme.
拒绝     不去?
Say no.          No?
是的 不去      好的 不去?
Yes, no.         Yes no?
是的 拒绝 最终决定      要是您这么想
Yes, say no! That's final. Lf that's what you want.
他们说了 就算您不露面 他们还会播出节目
But they would go ahead with the item
那时候可就没人替您维护了
and nobody would be there to state yourcase.
不去? 好吧 去
No? Okay, yes.
不去 好吧 去
No, okay, yes...
我懂您的意思      去
Oh, I see what you mean. Yes.
最后的最终意见?
Finallyfinal?
伯纳 谢谢
Thank you, Bernard.
汉弗莱 安全措施的问题我该怎么说?
What am I going to tell them about safeguards. Humphrey?
您可以提醒他们 大臣
Perhaps you could remind them, Minister,
冰冻三尺非一日之寒
that Rome wasn't built in a day?
汤姆
Tom.
我的朋友     介意我坐下吗?
Oh, my dearfellow.        Mind if I join you?
当然不
No, of course not.
当反对党的滋味如何?
Well, how are you enjoying being in opposition?
执政的感觉如何?
How are you enjoying being in Government?
实际上并非如我期望那般 此刻就不是
Well, not as much as I expected, actually.Well, not at the moment.
汉弗莱把你制服了?
Humphrey got you undercontrol?
想做成点事情真难
It's so hard to get things done.
你办成过什么事吗?      几乎没有
Did you manage to get things done? Oh, almost nothing.
我直到选举来临才摸透了他的战术
When I did cotton on to his technique, there was the election.
战术?       拖延战术
Technique? Stalling technique.
拖延战术?       有五个阶段
Stalling technique? It comes in five stages.
首先 他会跟你说内阁新建 尚有许多事务要处理
First, he'll tell you there's lots of things to be getting on with.
他今早就是这么多我说的      当然了
He told me that this morning.      Quite.
其次 如果你仍然坚持 他会这么说
Then, if you still persist, he'll say something like
"好的 大臣 意图很好
"Ah, yes, Minister, I quite appreciate the intention,
确实应该施行
certainly something ought to be done,
但你肯定这是实施它的正确方式?"
but are you sure this is the rightway to achieve it?".
我应该记下来
I must make a note of this.
如果你还没有被唬住 他会改变立足点
Now, if you are still undeterred, he will shift his ground.
从告诉你如何做转向何时做
He will shift from how to do it to when you should do it.
他会这么说
I mean, he'll say,
"大臣 现在不是恰当的时机
"Now, Minister, this is not the right time,
出于各种原因"
forall sorts of reasons".
大臣们就裹足不前了?      多数如此
And Ministers settle forthat?     Well, lots do.
如果你没有放弃
And if you don't,
他会说政策"拟定起来困难重重"
he'll say that the policy"has run into difficulties".
比方说?       技术上 行政上 法律上
Such as?        Technical, political, legal...
法律是最好的托词
Legal are the best sort.
他会使其听起来玄乎其玄
He can make those totally incomprehensible.
走运的话 这个战术会持续三年
And with any luck, this technique will have lasted forthree years
到了最后阶段 他会告诉你
and you'll be at the final stage when he says:
"大臣 下一届大选近在咫尺
"We're getting very close to the next general election.
你能确保这项政策通过?"
Are you sure you can get this policy through?"
三年 怎么能拖了三年?
Howhas it taken three years?
因为你不督促 汉弗莱爵士是绝对什么也不会做的
Sir Humphrey will do absolutely nothing unless you chase him.
而你偏偏还有一堆事情要做
And you've got fartoo much to do.
你瞧 他们称之为"创造的惰性"
You see, it's what they call "creative inertia".
你要设法通过什么政策?
What's the policy you're trying to get through anyway?
我试着让国家综合数据库
I'm trying to make this National Integrated Data Base
少些极权主义
a bit less of a Big Brother.
原来是这么回事
Oh, is that what it is?
他告诉你这是新政策 对吧?     是啊
He's told you it's all quite new? Well, yes.
我的朋友 这项法案我们耗了几年
My dearfellow, we spent years on that.
政府白皮书都写好了 可惜大选了
We had a White Paper when they called election.
这些我都做过
I've done it all.
那些行政麻烦呢?      全都解决了
And administrative problems? I've solved them.
他告诉你不能看先前的文件?
And you couldn't see any of the previous papers?
是的      不足为奇 他已经清盘了
yes No wonder. He's wiped the slate clean.
知道他下一步会怎样吗?
D'you knowwhat his next move's gonna be?
不知道      今晚给你几箱文件?
No. Howmany boxes have you got?
3箱? 4箱?       5箱
Three? Four?      Five.
他有没有跟你说过不要太担心第5箱?
Did he tell you not to worry about the fifth one?
是的     这就对了 我担保
Yes.           Right. I'll take a bet.
你会在第5个箱子底部找到一个备忘录
You will find at the bottom of the fifth box a memo
详细解释了为何
which explains exactly why
有关资料库的任何新举措必须暂缓
any newmoves on the Data Base
如果你没能发现
must be delayed. If you don't find it,
他将无须盲目行事 但6个月后
he won't do anotherblind thing, but in six month's time
他会说他早告诉你了
he'll say that he has told you all about it.
汤姆 你从政多年 对公务员的花招真是无所不晓
Tom you were inoffice foryears.You know allCivil Service tricks.
谈不上无所不晓 老兄 上百种花招而已
Not all, old boy. Just a fewhundred.
那么你是如何让他们违心行事的?
And how do you make them do something they don'twant to do?
亲爱的朋友 如果我知道就不会在野了
My dearfellow, if I knew that I wouldn't be in Opposition.
可我不理解 汤姆是反对党
But I don't get it. Tom's the opposition.
他为什么告诉你这些?
Why did he tell you all this?
反对党并不表示敌对      当然不 我犯糊涂了
The Opposition aren't the opposition. Of course not. Silly of me.
他们只是这么称呼     他们不过是在野的反对党
They are called that. They're the opposition in exile.
那些公务员才是在朝的反对党
The Civil Service are the Opposition in residence.
汤姆说在第5个盒子的底部
Now then, bottom of the fifth box, Tom said.
但就算你知道也无能为力
But you can't really do anything.
无能为力?
Oh, can't I?
资料库相关的文件汤姆都给我了
Tom's given me all his papers on the Data Base.
三年的价值
Three year's worth!
了不起
Marvellous!
找到了
Found it.
竟然被夹在长达80页的福利措施报告里
It had slipped into an 80 page report on Welfare procedures.
"安全措施仍在讨论
"Safeguards still underdiscussion...
计划悬而未决
programme not finalised...
"不可草率行动
nothing precipitate...
若无相左之指示 建议待发展再定夺"
failing instructions to the contrary, propose await developments".
老一套
Typical!
给汉弗莱打电话 说你不同意    我一早就会见他
Ring Humphrey and tell him. I'll see him first thing.
现在就打给他     现在可是凌晨2点
Ring him now!             It's two o'clock.
他正睡得香呢      要的就是这效果
He'll be fast asleep.            Exactly!
安妮
Annie.
凭什么他安稳入睡你却仍在工作?
Why should he be asleep and you're still working?
他害你白白忙活 现在轮到你整整他
He's had you on the run. Now it's yourturn.
我不能够这么做
I couldn't do that.
他电话多少?
What's his number?
何况材料在第5个盒子里 你根本无法早些看到
Itwas in the fifth box, you couldn't have got to it earlier.
有道理
True.
喂?
Yes?
汉弗莱 这么晚打扰你真不好意思
Humphrey, sorry to ring you so late.
我没破坏你晚餐的兴致吧?
I didn't interrupt you in the middle of dinner, did I?
没有 晚餐早结束了
No, we finished dinner some while ago.
现在几点了?
Oh, good. What's the time?
凌晨两点
Er, two a.m.
我的老天 出了什么大事?      没有 一切正常
Good God, what's the crisis? No. No crisis.
我正在研究盒子
I'm going through my boxes,
而且我知道你肯定也还在鞠躬尽瘁
and I knew you'd still be hard at it.
对的 对的 埋头苦干
Oh, yes, yes, yes, yes. Nose to the grindstone.
那好 我刚看到资料库的文件
Well, I've just come across this Data Base paper.
您发现... 您看过了
Oh, you've found... you've read it!
我得说这让我很不满
Thought I'd bettertell you I'm not happy with it.
你将有幸为此另寻出路
You'll welcome an opportunity to work on something else.
不介意我打电话给你吧     不 大臣 一点也不
You didn't mind my calling you? No. Not at all Minister.
听到您的声音总是非常愉快
Always a pleasure to hearfrom you.
糟了 我忘了告诉他内阁会议前来找我了
I meant to tell him to see me about it before Cabinet.
现在别打给他
Don't ring him now.
是啊 现在是晚了点
You're right, it is a bit late.
让他先睡10分钟
Give him anotherten minutes.
您最好速战速决
If you could be fairly quick.
他10点要参加内阁会议     我可以马上解决
He does have Cabinet at 10.      I can be very quick.
伯纳 "不行"是要对大臣说的最简洁的句子
The word "No" is one of the shortest in the language.
抱歉来晚了 今早有许多公文要读
Sorry to be so late. Lots of reading to do this morning.
伯纳 早安 谢谢 乔治
Good morning, Bernard. Thank you, George.
汉弗莱 资料库的事
Now, Humphrey, the Data Base.
你起草了安全措施的计划书了吗
Have you drafted yoursafeguards?
大臣 我十分欣赏您的意图
Well, Minister, I quite appreciate your intention
而且非常认同安全措施的必要性
and fully agree that there is need forsafeguards,
但是
but is this
这是实施它的正确方式吗?      是我的方式
the rightway to achieve it?        Well, it's my way.
一个对上了
One.
无论如何 我主意已定
That's my decision, anyway.
出于各种因素 现在不是恰当的时机
Well this is not really the time forall sorts of reasons.
两个
Two.
现在正是时候
It's the perfect time.
安全措施应该紧跟系统的步伐
Safeguards should be developed alongside systems,
这是常识
that's common sense.
之前我们已经有过各种尝试 实施起来困难重重
We tried all this before and we ran into all sorts of difficulties.
三个
Three.
比如?
Such as?
例如技术上     不 没问题
Well, technical, for instance. No. No problems.
我研究了 我们可以实施与美国国务院
We can use the same basicfile interrogation programme
以及瑞士内政部一样的审核程序
as the U.S. State Dept. And the Swedish Ministry of the Interior.
这个不成问题
No problems there.
好吧 但行政上存在极大的麻烦问题
Yes, but there are also formidable administrative problems.
各部门都会受到影响
And all departments are affected.
跨部门委员会...     不不不 汉弗莱
An interdepartmental committee... No. No. No, Humphrey.
我想你会发现 现行的安全手续足以胜任
You'll find that the existing security procedures are adequate.
只需简单地完善 还有吗?
This is simply an extension. Anything more?
还有 大臣     例如法律问题?
Well, yes, Minister. Legal problems, forexample?
对 大臣      很好 很好
Yes, Minister.      Good, good.
我们有法律权限吗?
Do we have the legal power?
我可以帮你解答 我们有
I'll answer it. We have.
工作人员的职权受到其协议的约束
All personnel affected are bound by theirstaff agreements.
是的 但大臣 这将需要额外配备公务员
Yes, but Minister, there will be a need forextra staffing.
你能让其在内阁和议会通过吗
Will you be able to get it through the parliamentary party?
是的 我确定可以 还有其它问题吗?
Yes, I'm quite sure. Anything further?
我看没了 我们可以着手去做了
I don't think so. We can go ahead then.
你不吭声啊 汉弗莱
You're very silent.
大臣 你似乎没意识到荆棘丛丛
You don't seem to realise the amount of work that's involved.
难道你曾调查过安全措施的问题?
Haven't you examined safeguards before?
在其他的内阁里?
Underanothergovernment?
我记得在议会上有过类似答辩
I remembersome written answers to parliamentary questions.
首先 我们说好的 这不能...
Well, in the first place as we've agreed that question is not...
其次 即便有过调查
In the second place, if there had been investigations,
其实要么没有 要么没必要
which there haven't ornot necessarily,
要么我无权透露
orl am not at liberty to say whetherthere have,
那就必然有过一个研究小组
there would have been a project team, which,
其存在过与否 我无可奉告
had it existed, on which I cannot comment,
即便存在过 也已经解散了
which would nowhave disbanded if it had existed
成员已经各自回到曾经的部门
and the members returned to do theirdepartments,
如果真的存在过这些成员的话
if indeed there had been any such members.
或者也可能从没存在过
Ornot as the case may be.
正是这样 大臣
Quite so, Minister. I want these safeguards
汉弗莱 我要安全措施立即实施
made available immediately.
大臣 根本不可能      可能
Minister, it is not possible.       It is.
不可能      可能
It isn't.         It is.
It isn't.           It is.
不可能     可能可能可能可能
It isn't.        'Tis, 'tis, 'tis, 'tis, 'tis, 'tis.
大臣 只是提醒您 内阁会议在10点举行
Just to remind you, you have Cabinet at 10.00,
1点参加英美协会
the Anglo American Society at one,
傍晚接受"聚焦世界"的采访
and the "World in Focus" interview, this evening.
连个吃饭的空都没有?
Can't you get me out of the lunch?
很抱歉 大臣 已经对外通告过了
I'm afraid not minister.It's been announced.
我想想 我以为我...
I see... I suppose I...
你刚说什么 伯纳?     我们不能更改 大臣
What's that you just said? We can't get out of it.
已经对外通告 已列入日程
It's been announced, it's in the programme.
谢谢 伯纳
Thank you, Bernard.
万分感谢
Thank you very much.
大臣 为什么?
Forwhat, Minister?
为一切 伯纳德
Foreverything, Bernard.
聚焦世界
今晚在座的是吉姆・哈克阁下
our Man ontheSpot tonightis the Right HonourableJim Hacker,
行政事务部大臣
MinisterforAdministrative Affairs,
老大哥计算机计划争论的中心人物
the man at the heart of the Big Brothercomputercontroversy.
他正在接受戈弗雷・芬奇的访问
He's talking to Godfrey Finch.
大臣
Minister,
如您所知 本周民众对于众所周知的
as you know there's been an outcry this week
公务员官僚部门正在为每个公民
about the dossierthat the Civil Service bureaucracy
建立个人档案一事 大声疾呼表示不满
has apparently been building up on every citizen in this country.
现在传言事实并非如此 您个人的政策是
Now, it's rumoured that this is not in fact, yourown policy,
您想为公民们实施安全措施
that you'd like to have safeguards forthe individual citizen,
但在玩弄权术的政治舞台上
but that you are being totally frustrated at every stage
您完全彻底地遭到了滑铁卢
of the game by the Civil Service machine.
要知道 戈弗雷
You know, Godfrey,
关于行政部门 颇多微词
there's a lot of nonsence talked about the Civil Service.
其实它是非凡而高效的专业机构
It's a marvellous, efficient, professional organisation,
充满活力 高速运转
capable of enormous energy and speed.
它汇集了许多有才干的无私奉献的人们
It's staffed by a lot of talented, dedicated people
正尽其所能帮助政府
who do everything in theirpower to help the Government
将政策转化为法律
make it's policies into law.
感谢您所做的广告 大臣
Well, thank you forthe commercial, Minister.
我们现在可以开始节目了吗?
Perhaps we can start the programme now?
实际上 行政部门和我
The fact of the matter is that the Civil Service and I
在整件事上的看法完全一致
are in complete accord overthis whole business
我在此高兴地宣布
and I'm happy to announce that we're nowready
我们已准备好 将此提议公之于众
to put ourproposals into publication.
事实上 今晚我可以说 从9月1日起
In fact, tonight I can say that from Septemberthe first,
英国每位公民都有绝对的权利
every citizen of the U.K. Will have the absolute right
查阅自己的私人档案 并核查
to inspect his personal file and check any information
任何他曾经向政府提供的信息
that he has eversupplied to the Government.
其次
Secondly,
没有大臣的许可 任何公务员将无权
no civil servant will be allowed to examine personal files
查阅其他部门的私人档案
from anotherdepartment, without written authorityfrom a Minister.
我在此宣布 下周将通过一项法案
And I shall be announcing in the House next week legislation
授权公民能向任何未经许可
enabling citizens to take legal action against any civil servant
查阅其档案的公务员提出诉讼
who gains unauthorised access to his file.
颇令人鼓舞 大臣
Encouraging, Minister.
您为何不早日宣布 让人民不必为此担心?
Why did you not say so first, and put people's minds at rest?
老实说 我不确信公务员能够按时完成
I didn't believe that the Civil Service could meet ourdeadlines.
但他们让我深信能够做到
But they've convinced me that they can.
而且事实上 我的常务秘书
And, in fact, my Permanent Secretary
以他的名誉向我担保
has staked his reputation on it.
一旦未果 引咎辞职
And if not, heads will roll...
当然 秘书表率
Anyway, Assistant Heads.
大臣 很感谢
Thank you very much, Minister.
不能施行      已经在电视上公布了
It can't be done. It's been announced on TV.
伯纳 你看大臣这是在干什么?
Bernard, what did you make of our Minister's performance?
我 我想这是将了您的军了 汉弗莱爵士
Well, I... I think it's check mate, Sir Humphrey.
汉弗莱 昨晚在电视上看到我了吗?
See me on the box last night, Humphrey?
当然看到了 大臣
Of course, Minister.
我表现如何? 不错?
Howwas I? Good?
精妙绝伦的演出
A most remarkable performance,
大臣 如果我可以这么评价的话
Minister, if I may say so.
你可以      谢谢 大臣
You may, you may. Thank you, Minister.
大臣 经过彻夜的辛苦工作
We have been working very hard all night,
我高兴地告诉您我们赶出了
and I'm happy to be able to tell you thatwe have come up
部分建议草案
with some draft proposals
可以让您在预定时间内
which would enable you to achieve your desired objectives
达成目标
by the stated dates.
做得不错 汉弗莱
Well done. Humphrey
你看 我告诉全国你十分杰出 此话非虚
I told the nation how splendid you were and I was right.
我对你非常有信心     的确如此 大臣
I had every confidence in you. Quite so, Minister.
你肯定经历了一个难以忘怀的夜晚
You must have had quite a night.
是 大臣 难忘之夜     瞧瞧你的提案吧
Yes, Minister, quite a night! Let's see yourproposals.
请过目
Here they are.
也来瞧瞧我的
And here are mine.
您也做了详细的建议书?
You have specific proposals too?
我确实做了
Oh, indeed I have.
汉弗莱 把你的安全措施念出来
Now, Humphrey, you read out what you've got on safeguards,
我同样念出我的 我们来对照下
and I'll read out what I've got and we'll see how they compare.
"个人资料 第一条:
"Personal data 1A:
安全措施必须以两项原则...
Safeguards must be applied with reference to...
为准绳
Two criteria.
有无必要与有无权利知道
The need to know and the right to know.
第一款 有无必要知道
1A1. The need to know
仅将那些
only those officials...
被提供信息的公务员
forwhom the information was submitted may be deemed,
初步视为有必要知道
prime facie, to have a need to know.
看来我们英雄所见略同 汉弗莱
We seem to be of the same mind, Humphrey.
的确 大臣
Indeed, Minister.
这个提案从哪得来的?
Where did those proposals come from?
大臣?
Minister?
听到我的话了吗?
Can you hearme?
这个提案从哪得来的?
Where did those proposals come from?
汉弗莱 我得守口如瓶
Humphrey, my lips are sealed.